Guide to the Creative Time Archive 1973-2006 MSS.179
Fales Library and Special Collections
Creative Time Archive
1973-2006
Fales Library and Special Collections
Creative Time, Inc.
MSS.179
56 Linear Feet (81 boxes)
Founded in 1973, Creative Time is a public art organization based in New York City. The organization has a history of commissioning, producing, and presenting public artworks of all disciplines. The material in the collection document all aspects of the creation, exhibition, and reception of these commissioned artworks, as well as invaluable financial records that reflect how the organization has sustained, promoted, and financially supported its mission.
Provenance
Creative Time donated their archive to Fales Library in September 2006.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Fales Library and Special Collections, fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Historical Note
Creative Time is a nonprofit arts organization founded in 1973 to support the creation of innovative, site-specific works by professional artists for public presentation in vacant spaces of historical and architectural interest throughout New York City. Its history of commissioning, producing, and presenting adventurous public artworks of all disciplines began in the midst of a significant period in which artists were experimenting with new forms and media that moved their works out of galleries and museums and into the public realm. At this time, New York's citizens were responding to the City's deterioration, which was prompted by the fiscal crisis, with the City Beautification movement. Additionally, the federal government, recognizing the significance of art in society, established the National Endowment for the Arts (NEA) to herald the role of artists and introduce uninitiated audiences to contemporary art. Creative Time derives its values from this historic impetus to foster artistic experimentation, enrich public space and the everyday experience, and forefront artists as key contributors to a democratic society.
Programs sponsored by Creative Time include both the visual and performing arts and are designed to encourage a dialogue between the artist and the community. By presenting new works by artists concerned in enhancing the viewer's perception of a particular environment, sharing with the public the creative process, and using densely populated locations lacking in cultural amenities, these new works have expanded the definition of public art.
Creative Time's reputation has not rested on having a readily identifiable home, but on an identifiable programming philosophy, which requires that it move around to take advantage of the city's richness of resources.
Their earliest programs invigorated vacant storefronts as well as neglected public spaces such as the Great Hall of the Chamber of Commerce in Lower Manhattan and the arches of the Brooklyn Bridge Anchorage. Both landmarks are overwhelming in their visual impact and wealth of history they represent. Until Creative Time's tenancy, the Great Hall had been closed for several years, and the arches for over a century. From 1983 - 2001, Creative Time presented Art in the Anchorage and the imposing and dramatic scale of the Anchorage arches drew thousands to the majestic chambers to view annual exhibitions of emerging creative practices in art, music, theater, and fashion until its closure in 2001 due to national security.
Creative Time gained early renown for initiating Art on the Beach on two acres of landfill known as Batter Park City, an area targeted for future residential and commercial development. From 1978 to 1985, this site became a laboratory for artists of all mediums to develop large scale works and often collaborate as interdisciplinary teams bringing together architects, sculptors, performers, musicians. Open free to the public for three months every summer, this unique program presented site-specific sculpture and performances. An eagerly anticipated event on New York's summer calendar of cultural happenings, the event relocated to Hunter's Point Queens for the summers of 1987-1988. The success of Art on the Beach set a model for the presentation of temporary public art which has since been adopted nation wide by city governments and other arts agencies.
Creative Time's Citywide program was inaugurated in 1989 and provided a new forum for further investigation of the parameters of public art. Responding to the impact of censorship and the art community's isolation, Creative Time noticed a need for individual artists to control and initiate the presentation of their work in public places and for the public to have greater access to artists and their process. Creative Time soon spread its programs throughout New York City. Presenting projects on billboards, landmark buildings, buses, deli cups, milk cartons, ATM machines, and the Internet, among numerous other venues, Creative Time broadened the definitions of both art and public space throughout the 1980s and 90s. In particular, Creative Time encouraged artists to address timely issues such as the AIDS pandemic, domestic violence, and racial inequality.
From 1973-1986, Creative Time was under the leadership of Anita Contini and continued until Cee Scott Brown took over as director in 1987. Anne Pasternak stepped in as director in 1993 and continues in this position at present. Today, Creative Time continues to provide hundreds of emerging and established artists with unparalleled opportunities to create ambitious new works that expand their practices and foster career growth. Each year, Creative Time also offers millions of people rare encounters with contemporary art beyond racial, economic, and age factors, thereby enlivening the everyday experience of New York City. While Creative Time delights New Yorkers with skywriting over Manhattan and colorful sculptures in Grand Central Station, it also inspires with projects like Tribute in Light, the twin beacons that rose from Lower Manhattan. Creative Time's alumni community continues to grow as the world's leading artists join the roster next to Vito Acconci, Diller + Scofidio, David Byrne, Felix Gonzalez-Torres, Red Grooms, Jenny Holzer, Takashi Murakami, Shirin Neshat, Sonic Youth, and Elizabeth Streb, among thousands more. Lastly, Creative Time has remained committed to promoting collaboration within the creative community, frequently partnering with institutions like the Dia Art Foundation, The Kitchen, Lincoln Center, the Metropolitan Museum of Art, MTA Arts for Transit, and the Whitney Museum of American Art.
References:
1. Creative Time website, creativetime.org, Creative Time, Inc. copyright 1974-2008.
2. Unknown author, untitled Creative Time press document, unpublished, circa 1985.
3. Creative Time: 20 years of art in unexpected places.
4. Pasternak, Anne and Ruth A. Peltason, ed. Creative Time: The Book, 33 Years of Public Art in New York City (New York: Princeton Architectural Press, 2007).
Scope and Content Note
The Creative Time Archive is an extremely diverse collection that comprehensively documents the on-going history of Creative Time, the New York City-based nonprofit arts organization. The collection contains a wealth of materials that document the organization's commitment to and history of commissioning, producing, and presenting adventurous public artworks of all disciplines. The bulk of the printed manuscript material spans from 1973- 1994 but includes documentation through the present. Additionally, there is much media material, particularly from the 1990s through early 2000s.
Materials in the Creative Time Archive reflect the intensely experimental and collaborative environment in which these artworks were created, as well as the ever-developing, ever-changing New York City landscape from the 1970s to the present. In addition, the materials reflect a global perspective in their representation of the shifting nature of artistic relations with the world at large. Given the time-based nature of much of the art that Creative Time was presenting, the organization was thorough in their documentation and includes extensive production and promotional materials that document all aspects of the creation, exhibition, and reception of these commissioned artworks. The collection also includes invaluable financial records that reflect how the organization sustains, promotes, and financially supports its mission.
Numerous oversize items found at the end of each of the series include design plots, posters, oversize printed matter and other promotional materials housed in boxes and map cases.
The Creative Time Archive is divided into eight series:
SERIES I: Exhibitions and Projects consists of correspondence, artist proposals, permits, artist biographies, administrative and production documentation, original art, flyers, invitations, promotional material, catalogs, related press, among other documents relating to the creation, exhibition, and reception of these individual projects and exhibitions. Projects/ exhibitions are arranged chronologically by year. Besides looking at individual project folders, researchers should also request any general folders from a given year as they may contain additional documentation. Additional material may be found in Oversize series.
SERIES II: Grants, Development and Financial Correspondence is divided into seven subseries and consists of financial records, grant proposals, budget documentation, correspondence, and ancillary supporting documentation. Originally arranged chronological by fiscal year, material has been re-organized to group chronologically by year as well as by grant funding agency. The content within individual folders reflects Creative Time's original order. Some projects corresponding to particular grant requests have been written in brackets in finding aid descriptions.
Subseries A: National Endowment for the Arts
Subseries B: NYSCA
Subseries C: DCA
Subseries D: Miscellaneous Grants
Subseries E: Development
Subseries F: Financial Correspondence
Subseries G: Funding
SERIES III: Slides contains all slides from the Creative Time Archive. Slides have been arranged into binders by project chronologically by year, respective of the order as received from Creative Time. Each sleeve has been given a unique alphanumeric designation according to binder arrangement. Slide content primarily includes exhibition and performance documentation and the majority of slides were received with substantial annotation as to the project, artist, date, and photographer. Subdividers before each project provide names of most photographers and artists represented therein.
SERIES IV: Photographic Materials includes all negatives, transparencies, contact sheets, and photographic prints from the Creative Time Archive. These substantial holdings are ordered chronologically by year and separated by individual project. Projects have been separated according to different types of material-negatives, contact sheets, and prints (the few transparencies in the archive have been housed with the negatives). Photographic content primarily includes exhibition and performance documentation along with promotional photos, artist samples, and site/planning prints. Many prints and contact sheets include substantial annotation as to the project, artist, date, and photographer.
SERIES V: Video and Film contains the videotaped material from the Creative Time Archive. Titles are arranged chronologically by year. Compilation tapes are arranged chronologically by first year represented on tape. Material includes performances, news broadcasts, source material, artist samples, and other miscellaneous recordings. There is a small amount of film material. Description of each item includes a title (which has been derived from cassette or container annotations), date, the original format of video, and total running time (TRT). Researcher access is limited to Subseries A: Video Recordings - Access Copies.
Subseries A: Video Recordings - Access Copies
Subseries B: Video Recordings - Originals
Subseries C: Film
SERIES VI: Audio includes audio recordings from the Creative Time Archive. Titles are arranged chronologically by year. Compilation tapes are arranged chronologically by first year represented on tape. Material includes performances, news broadcasts, speeches, source material, and other miscellaneous recordings. Researcher access is limited to Subseries A - Audio Recordings - Access Copies.
Subseries A: Audio Recordings - Access Copies
Subseries B: Audio Recordings - Originals
SERIES VII: Marcos Kurtycz - Mail Art materials consist of various mailed objects created by artist Marcos Kurtycz including postcards, correspondence, books, performance and exhibition flyers, posters, and many art objects sent between 1988 and 1990 to Debbie Levine and Cee Scott Brown of Creative Time. Kurtycz (1934-1996) was a Polish-born, Mexico-based artist who exhibited works and performed in Creative Time's "UP Tiempo!" program at El Museo del Barrio in 1988 [see program documentation in Series I, III, IV, V]. Additional mailed objects from Kurtycz may be found in Oversize Series.
OVERSIZE SERIES contains oversize materials from Series I, IV, and VII and includes exhibition catalogues, magazines, building proposals, photographic materials (including negatives, contact sheets, and prints), blueprints, posters, and hand-drawn mock-ups for exhibition catalogue.
Series I: Projects, Programs and Publications
Series IV: Photos
Series VII: Marcos Kurtycz - Mail Art
Arrangement
For the most part, materials are arranged by project and chronologically by year. Series I: Production related materials are arranged chronologically by year of production. Series II: Grant related material is arranged by type and then chronologically by year with subseries to separate the various grant funding agencies. Series III and IV: Photographs and slides are arranged chronologically by the year of the subject or production title that the materials document. Series V and VI: Video and audio recordings are also arranged chronologically by year of production title. Series VII: Marcos Kurtycz mail art is arranged chronologically by year.
All efforts were made to preserve the original arrangement of the collection.
Missing Title
Series I: Exhibitons and Projects
Series II: Grants, Development, and Financial Correspondence
Series III: Slides
Series IV: Photo Materials
Series V: Video and Film
Series VI: Audio
Series VII: Mail Art - Marcos Kurtycz
Oversize Series
Related Material at Fales Library and Special Collections
A.I.R. Gallery Archive (MSS.184)
Jay Blotcher Papers (MSS.137)
Fashion Moda Archive (MSS.091)
Judson Memorial Church Archive (MSS.094)
Mabou Mines Archive (MSS.133)
REPOhistory Archive (MSS.113)
Harold and Joyce Pomeroy Schwartz Public Art Archive (MSS.171)
Martha Wilson Papers (MSS.175)
David Wojnarowicz Papers (MSS.092)
Separated Material
There is no information about materials that are associated by provenance to the described materials that have been physically separated or removed.
Acetate film.; Queens (New York, N.Y.); Manhattan (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Minutes (administrative records); Urban transportation.; Public art spaces.; Color slides.; Color photographs.; Calendars.; Catalogs.; blueprints (reprographic copies); Art |x Management.; Artists |z New York (State) |z New York |x Political activity.; Art |x Finance.; Art patronage -- New York (State) -- New York.; New York (N.Y.).; Artists -- New York (State) -- New York.; Grant proposals.; Art and state.; Art patronage.; Public architecture.; Public art -- New York (State) -- New York.; Political activists.; Politics in art.; Performance art -- New York (State) -- New York -- Exhibitions.; Performance artists.; Modern dance -- New York (State) -- New York; Motion pictures |z United States.; Modern dance|z United States.; Avant-garde (Aesthetics) |z New York (State) |z New York |x History |y 20th century.; Installations (Art) -- United States.; Local transit.; Experimental theater -- New York (State) -- New York.; Family violence |x Prevention.; Alternative spaces (Arts facilities) -- New York (State) -- New York.; Correspondence.; AIDS activists -- New York (State) -- New York; Poetry.; Art -- Political aspects.; Art -- Exhibitions.; Art, American -- New York (State) -- New York -- 21st century; Art, Modern |z United States |y 20th century |v Exhibitions.; AIDS (Disease) |x Social aspects |z New York (State) |z New York.; Membership lists.; Financial records; Design drawings.; Minorities in art.; Ground plans.; Announcements.; Press releases.; Advertisements.; Brooklyn Bridge (New York, N.Y.); Black-and-white photographs.; Negatives (photographic); Art, American -- New York (State) -- 20th century.; Art -- Exhibitions -- New York (State) -- New York.; Manuscripts for publication.; Posters.; Audiotapes.; Transparencies.; Schematic drawings.; Contact sheets.; Programs (documents); Videocassettes.; Reviews (document genre); Clippings (information artifacts); Champagne, Lenora; Contini, Anita; Creative Time, Inc.; Dance Theater Workshop; Beckley, Connie, 1951-; Brand, Bill; Brown, Cee; Carlson, Ann, 1954-; Flanagan, Bob, 1952-1996; Forti, Simone; Fura dels Baus (Theater company); Diggs, Peggy; Diller, Elizabeth; Farley, Alice; Finley, Karen; Kelly, John, 1954-; Kalman, Tibor; Lower Manhattan Cultural Council; Kurtycz, Marcos; Holman, Bob, 1948-; Grooms, Red; Jones, Bill T.; Holzer, Jenny, 1950-; Oppenheim, Dennis, 1938-2011; New York State Council on the Arts; Pasternak, Anne, 1964-; Paik, Nam June, 1932-2006; Miralda, Antoni, 1942-; Station House Opera; Lutz, Adelle; New York (N.Y.). Department of Cultural Affairs; National Endowment for the Arts; Basinski, William, 1958-; B., Beth; Wojnarowicz, David; Anderson, Laurie, 1947-; ACT UP New York (Organization); Acconci, Vito, 1940-; Phillips, Liz, 1951-; Piene, Otto, 1928-; Gómez-Peña, Guillermo; Perron, Wendy; Scofidio, Ricardo; Snyder, Huck; Reynolds, Hunter; Riggs, Marlon T.; Ukeles, Mierle; Vawter, Ron; Streb, Elizabeth; Zwickler, Phil, 1955-1991; Wilson, Ann, 1931-; Wilson, Martha, 1947-; Gran Fury
- Series I: Exhibitions and Projects
  Scope and Contents note
  This series consists of correspondence, artist proposals, permits, artist biographies, administrative and production documentation, original art, flyers, invitations, promotional material, catalogs, related press, among other documents relating to the creation, exhibition, and reception of these individual projects and exhibitions. Projects/ exhibitions are arranged chronologically by year. Besides looking at individual project folders, researchers should also request any general folders from a given year as they may contain additional documentation. Additional material may be found in Oversize series.
  - Crafts in Action - Galleria, 100 William St, Feb 19 - Mar 19, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Clipping - "Galleria" article from Architecture Plus magazine, Sep/Oct 1974 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Sail - 88 Pine St, Dec 18, 1974 - Feb 21, 1975, 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Publication - "20 Years of Art in Unexpected Places" retrospective brochure (1974-1994), published by Creative Time, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Ruckus Manhattan - 88 Pine St, Nov 20, 1975 - Jan 20, 1976, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Publications - "Red Grooms and Ruckus Manhattan", Judd Tully (1977); Ruckus articles: Senior magazine, Jan 27, 1975 (vol.108, no.1); Art and Man magazine, Apr/May, 1976 (Vol.6, no.6), 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - New York Sky Events - East Harlem, June 10 - 11, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - New York Sky Events: Neon Rainbow - Central Park, June 26, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Anemones: An Air Aquarium - 88 Pine St, Oct 19 - Dec 31, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Anemones: An Air Aquarium - original flyer artwork, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Round: Sound for Concave Surfaces - US Custom House, 1 Bowling Green, Nov 19-21, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Custom and Culture 1 - US Custom House, 1 Bowling Green, June 29 - Sep 11, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Butler's Lives of the Saints - 88 Pine St, Dec 16, 1977 - Jan 28, 1978, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Letter - to Chairman of the Awards Committee [Commission of Cultural Affairs] about Morley Cho, [1977] (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Letter - recognition of tax exemption, from Internal Revenue Service, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Downtown Drive-In - Edison Parking Lot, July 28 - 29, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Art on the Beach 1 - Battery Park City Landfill, Aug 11 - Sep 17, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Press - general, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Publication - Art on the Beach retrospective program, published by Creative Time, 1985, 1978-1985 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Custom and Culture 2 - US Custom House, 1 Bowling Green, May 3 June 17, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Downtown Drive-in 2 - Edison Parking Lot, Aug 17-18, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence - general, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Press Kit, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Press - general, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Art on the Beach 2 - Battery Park City Landfill, June 14 - Sep 14, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Masstransiscope - Myrtle St Subway Station, Sep 17, 1980 - ongoing (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Projects at the Precinct House: Breaking In - First Precinct House, Oct 29 - Nov 15, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence - general, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Publication - Art on the Beach retrospective program (1980-1982), published by Creative Time, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Projects at the Precinct - First Precinct House, Mar 11 - Apr 4 1981 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Windspun - Hunter's Point, Bronx, May 13, 1981 - June 1, 1982, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Art on the Beach 3 - Battery Park City Landfill, June 20 - Sep 13, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Ruckus Manhattan Revival - Burlington House Lobby, 1345 Ave of the Americas, Dec 18, 1981 - Mar 31, 1982, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Children's drawings and writings, Ruckus Manhattan Revival, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Correspondence - general, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Press - general, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Principles in Perspective - Chamber of Commerce, June 22 - July 9, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Art on the Beach 4 - Battery Park City Landfill, June 26 - Sep 12, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Projects at the Chamber - Chamber of Commerce, Nov 9 - Dec 18, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Promo - holiday greeting card, gift certificate, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Press - general, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Art in the Anchorage 1 - Brooklyn Bridge Anchorage, May 19 - Oct 10, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Art on the Beach 5: Six Collaborative Projects - Battery Park City Landfill, July 9 - Sep 25, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Publication - Art on the Beach retrospective program (1985-1986), published by Creative Time, 1986, 1983-1985 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Press - on Brooklyn Bridge, press packet and articles, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Publication - The Diaries of Agatha Muldoon ed., published by Jane Greengold, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Correspondence - general, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Press packets - general, 1983-1985 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Press - general, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Walk-in Theater for Pedestrians - Thurgood Marshall US Courthouse, Jan 25 - Apr 12, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Art on the Beach 6 - Battery Park City Landfill, July 7 - Sep 16, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Touch Sanitation Show - Marine Transfer Station, 59th St, Sep 9 - Oct 5, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Nighttrippers - The Russian Baths, First Baptist Church, Oscar Hammerstein Opera House, Dec 1, 8, 15, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Promo - general, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Publication - Insights / On Sites: Perspectives on Art in Public Places [Creative Time article by Anita Contini], published by Partners for Livable Places, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 55)